A Guide to the Papers of John Calvin Metcalf 1904-1950
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Calvin Metcalf 1904-1950
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12714
This collection consists of ca. 180 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a bequest to the library from the Estate of Edmonia C. L. Metcalf on September 29, 1989.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 180 items (4 Hollinger boxes, ca. 1.3 linear shelf feet, and 4 oversized containers) and dates approximately from 1904 to 1950. It is comprised of John Calvin Metcalf's manuscripts of his literary and scholarly works, and of his book The Stream of English Biography. The collection has a relatively small quantity of personal material such as an honorary degree, banking records, and correspondence between Metcalf and his wife, Edmonia Carrington Lancaster Metcalf, publishers, University of Virginia professor Arthur Kyle Davis and University of Virginia historian Philip Alexander Bruce is also included.
In addition, this collection contains various items from his wife's estate including pictures of European scenes, a plaque of Athena, a shield depicting a medieval battle, and an engraved silver bowl presented to professor Metcalf.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged with all literary material in alphabetical order followed by two folders of fragments and notes and printed material with correspondence and personal papers placed alphabetically at the end. Oversized material [Mrs. Metcalf's items] are stored separately.
Contents List
- The American Novel n.d., 2 TMs (Box 1)
- American War Poetry n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- The Assumption of Graduate Work by Undergraduate Institutions n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- Browning, Artist and Philosopher [1924 Jan 30], TMs (Box 1)
- The Calling of the Scholars(incomplete) n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- The Club in Literature n.d., TMs (Box 2)
- Colleges and Culture n.d., 6 TMs (Box 1)
- Culture and Character n.d., 2 TMs (Box 1)
- Culture Versus Specialization n.d., 2 TMs (Box 1)
- Dante n.d., TMs, TMsS (Box 1)
- The Elizabethan Masque n.d., 2 TMs (Box 1)
- Greetings from American Universities n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- Thomas Hardy n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- Thomas Hardy, Last of the Victorians n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- Nathaniel Hawthorne n.d., 2 TMs (Box 1)
- Higher Education in Virginia for the Last 25 Years [1932 Feb 12], TMs (Box 1)
- The Humanizing of Robert Louis Stevenson [1926 Mar 10], TMsS (Box 1)
- The Idyl of Ruth(incomplete) n.d., AMs (Box 1)
- The Individual in Education n.d., TMs (Box 1)
- Rudyard Kipling, Story-Teller and Poet n.d., TMsS (Box 2)
- Knowledge and Power in Education n.d., 2 TMs, TMsS (Box 2)
- The Lesson of the Parables n.d., 2 TMs (Box 2)
- The Letter in Literature n.d., TMs (Box 2)
- A Liberal Education or What is a Liberally Educated Man n.d., TMsS (Box 2)
- Literature and Biography [1923 May 22], 2 TMs, TMsS (Box 2)
- Literature and Humor n.d., 2 TMs, TMsS (Box 2)
- Literature and the Machine Age n.d., 2 TMs (Box 2)
- Literature and Scholarship [1936 Dec 29], AMs, TMs (Box 2)
- Migratory Students n.d., TMs (Box 2)
- The New American Drama n.d., TMs (Box 2)
- An Old Romantic Triangle--A Comparative Study of Three Modern Dramas n.d., AMs, TMs (Box 2)
- An Old Romantic Triangle in Three Plays n.d., TMs (Box 2)
- Our Great Tradition n.d., TMsS, TMs (Box 2)
- Our Literature Today and Tomorrow n.d., TMsS (Box 2)
- Our Scandinavian Kin n.d., 2 TMsS (Box 2)
- The Romantic Beginnings: Charles Brockden Brown n.d., TMs (Box 3)
- Sanity and Sickness in Literature n.d., TMs (Box 3)
- Some Aspects of Modern Biography n.d., 5 TMs (Box 3)
- The Scholar's Utility n.d., TMs (Box 3)
- The Stream of English Biography [1930], TMs, 3 folders (Box 3)
- [The Stream of] English Biography n.d., TMs, carbon copy (Box 3)
- Leo Tolstoi, Artist and Moralist(incomplete) n.d., TMs (Box 3)
- Traditional Ballads of Virginia n.d., 2 TMs (Box 3)
- Untitled n.d., TMs (Box 4)
- Untitled n.d., TMs (Box 4)
- Untitled n.d., 2 TMs (Box 4)
- Untitled n.d., 2 TMs (Box 4)
- Untitled [1926 Oct 5], TMsS (Box 4)
- What is a Liberal Education? [1934 June 5], TMsS (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous Fragments and Notes n.d. (Box 4)
- Printed Material [1898-1928] (Box 4)
- Banking Records [1930] (Box 4)
- Correspondence with Edmonia Metcalf [1928-1929] (Box 4)
- Correspondence and Personal Papers- Miscellaneous [1904-1930] (Box 4)
- Correspondence from Publishers [1924-1927] (Box 4)
- pictures n.d. (Box 4)